Guide to the Peter Beste and Lance Scott Walker Houston Rap Collection
University of Houston Libraries
Peter Beste and Lance Scott Walker Houston Rap Collection
1986-2014
06/2015-008
Beste, Peter; Walker, Lance Scott
9.00 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection consists of materials related to the creation and production of the book Houston Rap, by photographer Peter Beste and writer Lance Scott Walker. These materials include digital photos taken by Beste, audio recordings and transcripts of interviews conducted by Walker, photo prints from the editing process of the book, exhibit prints of photos from the book, photo contact sheets, and dummy copies of the book.
Biographical Information:
Peter Beste is a documentary photographer originally from Houston and now based in New Mexico and New York City. In the early 2000s, he spent six years working on his book True Norwegian Black Metal, for which he photographed several Norwegian black metal bands. After that project, he brought this documentary approach back to his hometown to explore the development of Houston hip hop.
Houston Rap, published in 2013 by Sinecure Press, is the joint creation of Beste and Lance Scott Walker. The product of nearly a decade of work, it documents Houston’s hip hop community, particularly in the Third Ward, Fifth Ward, and South Park neighborhoods. Comprised of photographs by Beste interspersed with excerpts from interviews conducted by Walker, the book features a wide swath of rappers, producers, and other members of Houston’s hip hop community. The rappers run the gamut from the very famous, like Bun B and Geto Boys, to the virtually unknown. The photographs often show the subjects in unguarded personal moments, revealing a world very unlike what the public sees on album covers and promotional materials. The interviews provide further insight into the communities and stories described in the artists’ lyrics.
Lance Scott Walker is a journalist, and native Texan, who has written for many publications, including the Houston Chronicle, Houston Press, USA Today, and RollingStone.com. Extended versions of the oral histories conducted by Walker for Houston Rap can be found in its companion, Houston Rap Tapes.
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Corporate Name:
Screwed Up Click (Musical group); South Park Coalition
Genre/Form of Material:
Interviews; Photographs; Promotional materials
Personal Name:
Beste, Peter; DJ Screw, 1971-2000; Walker, Lance Scott
Topical Term:
Hip-hop -- Texas -- Houston; Rap (Music) -- Texas -- Houston; Rap musicians -- Texas -- Houston
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Related Materials:
Houston Rap https://library.uh.edu/record=b6199813~S11
Physical Characteristics or Technical Requirements:
Digital archival materials can be accessed in the Special Collections Reading Room by advance request. These materials may require up to one week to access. Contact Julie Grob at jgrob@uh.edu for more information.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of materials related to the creation and production of the book Houston Rap, by photographer Peter Beste and writer Lance Scott Walker. These materials include digital photos taken by Beste, audio recordings and transcripts of interviews conducted by Walker, photo prints from the editing process of the book, exhibit prints of photos from the book, photo contact sheets, and dummy copies of the book. The collection also contains a significant amount of material collected by the authors from various Houston hip hop artists, including recorded music, t-shirts, towels, posters, promo cards, and other memorabilia. The collection is divided into four series: Digital Files, Houston Rap Production and Promotion, Hip Hop Promotional and Research Material, and Music and Video. An important note: many of the materials found within the Digital Files series contain subject matter that would fit into other series within this collection.
Detailed List of Contents
- Digital files
  This series contains all of the digital materials received from Peter Beste and Lance Scott Walker, including digital photos, video, and interview audio files. Digital archival materials can be accessed in the Special Collections Reading Room by advance request. These materials may require up to one week to access. Contact Julie Grob at jgrob@uh.edu for more information.
  - Documentary Photos
    This sub-series consists of nearly 25,000 files from a hard-drive belonging to Peter Beste. It includes thousands of documentary photographs, various versions of and promotional materials for the book Houston Rap, scans and photos of ephemera collected from Houston hip hop artists, and video and audio files. All of the materials in this sub-series are found within a top-level folder on the hard drive entitled “HOUSTON.” The sub-sub-series represent the second-level folders in the hierarchy, and the folders within each represent the third-level folders in the hierarchy. Sub-sub-series and folder titles are taken directly from the hard drive. Digital archival materials can be accessed in the Special Collections Reading Room by advance request. These materials may require up to one week to access. Contact Julie Grob at jgrob@uh.edu for more information.
    - HOUSTON EPHEMERA
      This sub-sub-series contains photographs, postcards, and audio files collected from Houston hip hop artists, photographs taken of materials from the Hip Hop collections at the University of Houston, and other Houston hip hop ephemera collected by Walker and Beste.
      - AL D STUFF (Folder 1)
      - CONVERSATIONS WITH CHOICE 2005 (Folder 2)
      - EPHEMERA • OTHER HOUSTON (Folder 3)
      - KYU BOI STORIES (Folder 4)
      - MISC HOUSTON (Folder 5)
      - PHOTOS BY GONZO (Folder 6)
      - Poor recordings from 5th ward with willie d in 2004 (Folder 7)
      - POSTCARDS (Folder 8)
      - SCREW TITLES (Folder 9)
      - UH COLLECTION (Folder 10)
      - WICKET CRICKETT SCANS (Folder 11)
    - HOUSTON RAP BOOK
      This sub-sub-series contains materials related to the production and promotion of the book Houston Rap.
      - COVER IDEAS (Folder 1)
      - HRB PROMO • PRESS (Folder 2)
      - IN-PROGRESS EDITS (Folder 3)
      - • GONZO SLIPCASE (Folder 4)
      - • HOUSTON BOOK PITCH (Folder 5)
    - HOUSTON VIDEOS
      This sub-sub-series contains videos taken of members of the Houston hip hop community, usually either as part of an interview or for short promotional videos for the book Houston Rap.
      - 2011 HOUSTON RAP DROPS (Folder 1)
      - DEVIN BBQ VIDS (Folder 2)
      - Devin in the studio (Folder 3)
      - DEVIN SHOOT VID (Folder 4)
      - Early Dope E + Kyu Boi vids 2005 BY Christopher Rosales (Folder 5)
      - GANXSTA NIP PLAYS ME HIS NEW ALBUM AT THE CAR WASH (Folder 6)
      - GRACE VIDS (Folder 7)
      - HOUSTON VIDS 10 • 12 (Folder 8)
      - REED LOUNGE VIDS (Folder 9)
      - Z-RO INTERVIEW (Folder 10)
      - • PETER BESTE ON NORWEGIAN TV (Folder 11)
      - • SCREWED IN HOUSTON (Folder 12)
      - • • HOUSTON RAP DROPS (Folder 13)
    - • • HOUSTON DIGITAL
      This series contains thousands of documentary photos taken by Peter Beste while working on the book Houston Rap.
      - 2007 (Folder 1)
      - 2008 (Folder 2)
      - 2009 (Folder 3)
      - 2011 (Folder 4)
      - 2012 (Folder 5)
      - 2013 (Folder 6)
      - DAT BOY GRACE (Folder 7)
      - DEVIN BBQ (Folder 8)
      - DEVIN THE DUDE – COUGHEE POT (Folder 9)
      - DIGITAL RAW FOR RAP TAPES (Folder 10)
      - GANXSTA NIP (Folder 11)
      - K-RINO TRILOGY SHOOT (Folder 12)
      - Mike Jones XXL (Folder 13)
      - PAUL WALL XXL (Folder 14)
      - PIMP C PHOTOS (Folder 15)
      - REED LOUNGE (Folder 16)
      - SCARFACE XXL (Folder 17)
      - SCENIC RAW (Folder 18)
      - STRIPCLUBS (Folder 19)
      - TERRORISTS ALBUM SHOOT (Folder 20)
      - UGK XXL (Folder 21)
    - • • HOUSTON FILM •
      - HOUSTON RAP SLIDESHOW (Folder 1)
      - • HIGH RES SCANS (Folder 2)
      - • LOW RES (Folder 3)
  - Interviews
    This sub-series contains audio files and/or transcripts of interviews conducted by Lance Scott Walker with members of Houston’s hip hop community from 2005 to 2013. Each folder in this sub-series corresponds to a person who was interviewed and items within each folder represent audio files and transcripts associated with that person. Folders are arranged alphabetically by name, and folder descriptions were taken directly from an inventory provided by Beste and Walker. Digital archival materials can be accessed in the Special Collections Reading Room by advance request. These materials may require up to one week to access. Contact Julie Grob at jgrob@uh.edu for more information.
    - Al-B a.k.a. Elite Albee (Royal Flush) Interview, May 2012 (Folder 1)
      Member of the pioneering Houston rap group Royal Flush, who first emerged as battle rappers at the legendary Rhinestone Wrangler nightclub and later went on to release two albums on Rap-A-Lot. Topics include the late rapper Pimp C and his seldom-discussed religious beliefs. telephone interview (May 2012) audio.
      - Al-B aka Elite Albee (LSW 05-25-12).mp3 (Folder 1, Item 1)
      - interview - Al-B of Royal Flush (05-25-2012).pdf (Folder 1, Item 2)
    - Al-D Interview, 2010, March 2012 (Folder 2)
      Brother of the late DJ Screw and member of the Screwed Up Click who started his career with Houston label Jam Down Records. interview (2010) transcript + audio; telephone interview (March 2012) audio
      - interview - Al-D The Lion (03-2012).pdf (Folder 2, Item 1)
      - interview - Al-D The Lion (2010).pdf (Folder 2, Item 2)
    - Ashlei Mayadia (Folder 3)
      - interview - Ashlei Mayadia (Fall 2013).pdf (Folder 3, Item 1)
    - B-1 Interview, 2010 (Folder 4)
      Lesser known member of the South Park Coalition from Missouri City. Interview focuses on South Park and the scene surrounding it in the late '80s and early '90s. telephone interview (Fall 2010) transcript + audio
      - B-1 (LSW 10-2010).mp3 (Folder 4, Item 1)
      - interview - B-1 South Park Coalition (10-2010).pdf (Folder 4, Item 2)
    - Bamino a.k.a BAM Interview, April 2012, May 2012 (Folder 5)
      Houston entrepreneur and record producer who owns and operates Bam’s Auto Detailing in South Park, a community hub often talked about in Houston rap songs. He is the brother of Screwed Up Click member Mike-D, a.k.a. Bosshog Corleone. telephone interview (April 2012) audio; telephone interview (May 2012) audio
    - Big Mike Interview, 2011 (Folder 6)
      Former member of Convicts and Geto Boys whose real success came as a solo artist in the mid-'90s. He was later involved in a criminal incident of arson involving a Rap-A-Lot Records location and was imprisoned for years, now free and making music again. telephone interview (Summer 2011) transcript + audio
      - interview - Big Mike (Summer 2011).pdf (Folder 6, Item 1)
    - Big Tho, November 2011 (Folder 7)
      Strip club promoter who provided access to after hours spots. telephone interview (November 2011) transcript + audio
      - Big Tho (LSW 12-2011).mp3 (Folder 7, Item 1)
      - interview - Big Tho (11-2011).pdf (Folder 7, Item 2)
    - Born 2wice a.k.a B-2 Interview, May 2012 (Folder 8)
      Rapper/producer who was an early member of the group Royal Flush and is still an active producer. telephone interview (May 2012) audio
      - Born 2wice (LSW 05-30-12).mp3 (Folder 8, Item 1)
      - text - Born 2wice (05-30-12).pdf (Folder 8, Item 2)
    - Brooke Hi-10 (Folder 9)
      - Brooke Hi-10 (10-24-12).pdf (Folder 9, Item 1)
    - Bun B Interview, 2006, 2012 (Folder 10)
      Port Arthur born and raised rapper who was one half of UGK along with the late Pimp C. One of the most popular rappers in Houston. interview (2006) transcript + audio interview by Peter Beste (2012) audio + video
      - Bun B (LSW PB 09-2006).mp3 (Folder 10, Item 1)
      - interview - Bun B (05-29-12).pdf (Folder 10, Item 2)
      - interview - Bun B (2006).pdf (Folder 10, Item 3)
    - Captain Jack Interview, 2011 (Folder 11)
      Important figure in Houston who has been an active MC and promoter in the rap community since the 1970s and is still part of the city's nightlife. He released one of the first Houston rap records with his single “Jack It Up” in 1984. telephone interview (Fall 2011) transcript + audio
      - Captain Jack (LSW 2011).mp3 (Folder 11, Item 1)
      - interview - Captain Jack (Fall 2011).pdf (Folder 11, Item 2)
    - Chingo Bling Interview, April 2012 (Folder 12)
      Latino rapper best known for his 2007 album They Can’t Deport Us All. telephone interview (April 2012) audio
      - Chingo Bling (LSW 04-04-12).mp3 (Folder 12, Item 1)
      - interview - Chingo Bling (09-2012).pdf (Folder 12, Item 2)
    - Chris Ward Interview, May 2012 (Folder 13)
      Younger member of the Screwed Up Click and also part of Slim Thug’s group Boss Hogg Outlawz. telephone interview (May 2012) audio
      - Chris Ward (LSW 05-01-12).mp3 (Folder 13, Item 1)
    - Cl’Che Interview, 2010 (Folder 14)
      Veteran rapper and notable voice in the South Park community in which her grandparents owned and operated the MLK Nite Club until Hurricane Ike destroyed it in 2008. telephone interview (Summer 2010) transcript + audio
      - Cl' Che (LSW 05-17-14).mp3 (Folder 14, Item 1)
      - Cl' Che (LSW 2010).mp3 (Folder 14, Item 2)
      - interview - Cl'Che (Summer 2010).pdf (Folder 14, Item 3)
    - Cory Mo Interview, 2007 (Folder 15)
      Rapper/Producer who had at the time of the interview had already worked with UGK, Devin the Dude and Willie D before later relocating to Atlanta. telephone interview(2007) transcript
      - interview - Cory Mo (2007).pdf (Folder 15, Item 1)
    - Craig “BBC” Long Interview, 2008 (Folder 16)
      Veteran MC, b-boy, artist, and promoter active in Houston since the late 1980s. telephone interview (September 2008) transcript
      - interview - Craig (BBC) Long (2007).pdf (Folder 16, Item 1)
    - Creeplobama Interview, May 2012 (Folder 17)
      Part of the newer wave of Houston rappers and one of very few artists from Baytown. telephone interview (May 2012) audio
    - Darryl Scott Interview, 2007, May 2012 (Folder 18)
      Houston DJ who started in the 1970s and pioneered the slowed down sound that DJ Screw would later adopt into his own genre. His mixtapes were the most popular in Houston's urban community throughout the 1980s. telephone interview (2007) transcript. telephone interview (May 2012) audio
      - interview - Darryl Scott (2007).pdf (Folder 18, Item 1)
    - Def Jam Blaster (Folder 19)
      - article - Def Jam Blaster (10-2014).pdf (Folder 19, Item 1)
    - DeMo Interview, October 2011, March 2012 (Folder 20)
      The most popular Screwtape ever is June 27th, and it is Demo Sherman’s birthday tape. He is from Long Drive in South Park. telephone interview (October 2011) transcript + audio telephone interview (March 2012) audio
      - DeMo Sherman (LSW).mp3 (Folder 20, Item 1)
      - interview - Demo Sherman (03-2012).pdf (Folder 20, Item 2)
    - DenDen Interview, 2005 (Folder 21)
      Owner and operator of Straight Profit Records. interview (2005) transcript
      - interview - Den Den (2005).pdf (Folder 21, Item 1)
    - Derrick D-Reck Dixon Interview, 2013, April 2014 (Folder 22)
      Owner and operator of Wreckshop Records, home of the late Fat Pat and the late Big Moe. telephone interview (2013) audio. interview (April 2014) transcript + audio
      - interview - Derrick D-Reck Dixon (04-2014).pdf (Folder 22, Item 1)
    - D-Red Interview, 2010 (Folder 23)
      Producer and rapper for the Cloverland group Botany Boys. Conversations about DJ Screw and codeine cough syrup. telephone interview (Summer 2010) transcript + audio
      - interview - D-Red (Summer 2010).pdf (Folder 23, Item 1)
    - DiamondNicque Interview, 2011 (Folder 24)
      Los Angeles transplant who is the promoter and manager for many artists in Houston. She worked closely with the late rapper Hawk. telephone interview (Summer 2011) transcript + audio
      - Diamondnique Jasmin Turner.mp3 (Folder 24, Item 1)
      - interview - DiamondNicque Turner (Summer 2010).pdf (Folder 24, Item 2)
    - DJ Chill Interview, 2008, March 2012 (Folder 25)
      Early friend of DJ Screw and still an active DJ all around Houston. Also runs a screen printing operation on the Southside. interview (2008) transcript + audio. telephone interview (2008) audio. telephone interview (March 2012) audio
      - DJ Chill (LSW 2008).mp3 (Folder 25, Item 1)
      - interview - DJ Chill (2008).pdf (Folder 25, Item 2)
      - interview - DJ Chill (2009).pdf (Folder 25, Item 3)
      - interview - DJ Chill South Park (2008).pdf (Folder 25, Item 4)
    - DJ Cipher Interview, June 2012 (Folder 26)
      Longtime Houston DJ and member of the radio collective Kracker Nuttz. Native of South Park. telephone interview (June 2012) audio
      - DJ Cipher (LSW 06-05-12).mp3 (Folder 26, Item 1)
      - interview - DJ Cipher (06-05-12).pdf (Folder 26, Item 2)
    - DJ DMD Interview, 2011 (Folder 27)
      Port Arthur born and raised DJ, producer, and rapper who wrote the 1998 hit “25 Lighters,” and later became a Christian minister in Houston. telephone interview (Summer 2011) transcript + audio
      - DJ DMD (LSW Summer 2011).mp3 (Folder 27, Item 1)
      - interview - DJ DMD (Summer 2011).pdf (Folder 27, Item 2)
    - DJ Domination a.k.a. DJ Domo Interview, 2007 (Folder 28)
      Longtime DJ for Geto Boys, Scarface, and Devin the Dude. interview (2007) transcript
      - interview - DJ Domo (2007).pdf (Folder 28, Item 1)
    - DJ Gold Interview, 2011, 2012 (Folder 29)
      Lesser known member of the Screwed Up Click who now promotes a strip club on the South side of Houston near Missouri City. telephone interview (October 2011) transcript + audio. telephone interview (March 2012) audio
      - DJ Gold SUC (October 2011).mp3 (Folder 29, Item 1)
      - interview - DJ Gold (10-2011).pdf (Folder 29, Item 2)
    - DJ Grayface (Folder 30)
      - DJ Grayface (LSW 06-19-12).mp3 (Folder 30, Item 1)
      - text - DJ Grayface 06-09-12.pdf (Folder 30, Item 2)
    - DJ Oakcliff (Folder 31)
      - text - DJ Oakcliff (06-2012).pdf (Folder 31, Item 1)
    - DJ Styles (Folder 32)
      - article - DJ Styles (01-2015).pdf (Folder 32, Item 1)
    - Dope E. of The Terrorists Interview, 2007, 2010 (Folder 33)
      Legendary Houston rapper and producer who is a founding member of the South Park Coalition and the early Rap-A-Lot artists The Terrorists. He has produced tracks for many Houston rappers over the years, and still makes records — now from his home base of Austin, TX. Also uses the alias Murdoq. telephone interview (Summer 2007) transcript. telephone interview (Fall 2010) transcript
      - Dope E (October 2010).mp3 (Folder 33, Item 1)
      - interview - Dope E (2007).pdf (Folder 33, Item 2)
      - interview - Dope E (2010).pdf (Folder 33, Item 3)
    - Dougie D Interview, 2007 (Folder 34)
      Member of the group Guerilla Maab with Trae tha Truth and Z-Ro. interview by Peter Beste (2007) transcript
      - interview - Dougie D (2007).pdf (Folder 34, Item 1)
    - Enjoli Parker Interview, March 2012 (Folder 35)
      Female rapper who was a part of DJ Screw’s Screwed Up Click. telephone interview (March 2012) audio
      - Enjoli Parker SUC (LSW 03-23-12).mp3 (Folder 35, Item 1)
    - E.S.G. Interview, 2005 (Folder 36)
      Louisiana-born rapper whose career took off with the 1995 hit "Swangin' & Bangin'." Member of the Screwed Up Click and a big player in the squashing of the Northside/Southside war that plagued Houston throughout the 1990s when he reached out to collaborate with Northside rapper Slim Thug. E.S.G. stands for "Everyday Street Gangsta." interview (2005) transcript
      - interview - E.S.G. (2005).pdf (Folder 36, Item 1)
    - G-Dash Interview, 2006 (Folder 37)
      President of Swishahouse Records. interview (2006) transcript
      - interview - G-Dash (2006).pdf (Folder 37, Item 1)
    - Hollywood Floss Interview, December 2012 (Folder 38)
      One of a newer wave of Houston. telephone interview (December 2012) audio
      - interview - Hollywood FLOSS (12-2011).pdf (Folder 38, Item 1)
    - Icey Hott Interview, April 2012 (Folder 39)
      DJ and producer from the group Street Military. Interviewed along with longtime collaborator Mr. Baldhead, who appeared in the Vice documentary "Screwed In Houston" in 2007. telephone interview (April 2012) audio
      - Icey Hott (LSW 04-02-12).mp3 (Folder 39, Item 1)
      - interview - Icey Hott 04-02-12.pdf (Folder 39, Item 2)
    - Jazzie Redd (Folder 40)
      - Jazzie Redd (LSW 05-2012).mp3 (Folder 40, Item 1)
    - Justice Allah Interview, October 2010, November 2011, March 2012 (Folder 41)
      Rapper and radio host who is a powerful voice in the Houston community. Member of the South Park Coalition and the group The 144 ELiTE along with K-Rino, Dope E and Ashlei Mayadia. Hosts the radio program Friday Eve along with Optimo Ram. telephone interview (October 2010) transcript + audio. telephone interview (November 2011) transcript + audio. telephone interview (March 2012) audio
      - Justice Allah (LSW 2010).mp3 (Folder 41, Item 1)
      - interview - JusTice AllaH (10-2010).pdf (Folder 41, Item 2)
      - interview - JusTice AllaH (11-2011).pdf (Folder 41, Item 3)
    - Kathy Payton Interview, March 2012 (Folder 42)
      Fifth Ward developer and community planner. telephone interview (March 2012) audio
    - Kay-K Interview, 2007 (Folder 43)
      Rapper and member of the Screwed Up Click who is the only living member of the original Dead End Alliance (DJ Screw, Fat Pat, Hawk). telephone interview (2007) transcript
      - interview - Kay-K DEA (2007).pdf (Folder 43, Item 1)
    - KB Da Kidnappa Interview, 2011 (Folder 44)
      Original member of the group Street Military. telephone interview (Summer 2011) transcript + audio
      - KB Da Kidnappa (08-2011).mp3 (Folder 44, Item 1)
      - article - KB Da Kidnappa (10-2011).pdf (Folder 44, Item 2)
      - interview - KB Da Kidnappa (Summer 2011).pdf (Folder 44, Item 3)
    - Klondike Kat Interview, May 2012 (Folder 45)
      Early member of the South Park Coalition and unofficial member of Street Military interviewed soon after being released from prison. telephone interview (May 2012) transcript + audio
      - Klondike Kat (05-23-12).mp3 (Folder 45, Item 1)
      - interview - Klondike Kat (05-23-12).pdf (Folder 45, Item 2)
    - K-Otix (Micah Henderson and Damien Randle) Interview, 2008 (Folder 46)
      Damien Randle and Micah Nickerson of the group K-Otix (which also featured The ARE) on writing the “George Bush Doesn't Care About Black People” song. telephone interview (Summer 2008) transcript
      - interview - K-otix (2008).pdf (Folder 46, Item 1)
    - K-Rino Interview, 2006, October 2010 (Folder 47)
      One of the earliest rappers in Houston and founder of the South Park Coalition. Member of the groups C.O.D. (with Dope E) and The 144 ELiTE. One of Houston’s most prolific rappers. interview (2006) transcript + audio. interview (October 2010) transcript + audio
      - K-Rino (09-2006).mp3 (Folder 47, Item 1)
      - interview - K-Rino email (2005).pdf (Folder 47, Item 2)
      - interview - K-Rino home (2005).pdf (Folder 47, Item 3)
      - interview - K-Rino VBS (2006).pdf (Folder 47, Item 4)
    - Kuwait Interview, 2007 (Folder 48)
      Southside rapper who gave us a tour around South Acres. interview (2007) transcript
      - interview - Kuwait (2005).pdf (Folder 48, Item 1)
    - Kyu Boi Interview, 2007 (Folder 49)